Preliminary Inventory to the William Yandell Elliott papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Educational television (Box 111)
- AD HOC Committee re: Departmental Appointments, 1943-1959
- Beer, Samuel
- Business Advisory Council
- Civil Service applications for WYE recommendation
- Clayton, Will, 1945-1953
- Commission on Foreign Economic Policy
- McNeil Lowry and Ford Foundation
- Outside organizations - Atlantic Union, etc., 1949-1952 (Box 112)
- President's Committee on Administrative Management
- Department of State and other government memos
- National Security Council
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 113)
- Woodrow Wilson Foundation (Box 114)
- Woodrow Wilson Foundation (Box 115)
- Foreign Policy text
- Old papers
- Civilian control over the military in the formation of foreign policy
- Woodrow Wilson Foundation (Box 116)
- Miscellany (Box 117-122)
- American Institute of Public Opinion, gallup surveys, 1937-1938 (Box 123)
- Miscellany
- American Automobile Association (Box 124)
- American Bar Association
- American Birth Control League
- American Civil Liberties Union
- American Farm Bureau Federation
- American Federation of Labor
- American Institute on Weights and Measures
- American Legislators Association
- American Manganese Producers Association
- American Medical Association
- American Political Science Association
- American Public Welfare Association
- American Red Cross
- Anti-Saloon League
- Association Against the Prohibition Amendment
- Farm Federation Bureau
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 125-126)
- Colmer Report, 1946-1947 (Box 127)
- Senate Foreign Relations Committee
- Better Management in Wartime Government
- BEW - WPB
- Foreign Affairs Committee
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 128-133)
- Interstate trade barriers, 1939-1940 (Box 134)
- Defense Council, / Communist Tactics and Strategy, 1941
- Correspondence, 1942
- Crank file, / Miscellany, 1940-1941
- To Professor Elliott from Wheeler (Box 135)
- Old drafts Rousseau
- Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 136)
- Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 137)
- Office of Civilian Requirements, Task Committee and Advisory Council, 1944-1945 (Box 138)
- The World Trade Foundation Public Opinion Poll, 1946
- Office of Civilian Requirements, Task Committees and Advisory Council, 1944-1945 (Box 139)
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 140-145)
- Office of Civilian Requirements, Advisory Council meetings, 1944-1945 (Box 146)
- Miscellany
- Office of Civilian Requirements, Advisory Council meeting, January 1945 (Box 147)
- Daily Progress Report, 1944
- Council for Democracy
- WRUL
- OPM
- Miscellany
- Chronological file, 1941, 1942, 1944 (Box 148)
- Chronological file, 1944-1945 (Box 149)
- Industrial Mobilization for War - History of the War Production
- Board and Predecessor Agencies, 1940-1945
- Miscellany (Box 150)
- Miscellany (Box 151)
- Chronological file, 1944-1945
- Office of Civilian Requirements, 1944 (Box 152)
- Chronological file, August 1945
- War Production Board, 1945
- ODM business
- Motion pictures - propaganda value
- Select Relief Committees, 1948
- Herter correspondence
- Marshall Plan
- HR 4579
- C.A.H.
- Miscellany
- Daily Progress Report, 1945 (Box 153)
- Miscellany
- Draft report on Latin America (Box 154)
- Hoover memorandum
- Staff memoranda
- Dulles and draft "The Mechanism"
- Dispatches
- Miscellany
- Foreign Aid, 1947 (Box 155)
- Letters from Europe
- Select Committee Foreign Aid
- W.Y. Elliott, personal, 1948
- War Production Board
- Office of Defense Mobilization, 1951-1958 (Box 156)
- Memoranda from W. Y. Elliott to superior officers
- Supper and Final Report
- Correspondence with Departments and Embassies
- Republican leadership letters
- Documents for Study Reports
- Senate Committee on Expenditures in the Executive Departments
- Foreign Aid Bill
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 157)
- WYE tutorial (Box 158)
- G.S.P.A.
- WIXAL, 1938-1940
- Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1928-1932 (Box 159)
- Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 160)
- Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 161)
- Correspondence, 1935-1938 (Box 162)
- Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 163)
- UNESCO (Box 164)
- Education Exchange Program
- University contracts abroad, 1959
- Estes memoranda, 1960-1961 (Box 165)
- Department of State
- Public Law 480
- Biographies
- Miscellany
- Nixon, Richard M. (Box 166)
- Business Advisory Council, 1938-1952, 1961-1962 (Box 167)
- "American-New Countries Cooperation in Educational Training," edited by W.Y. Elliott, 1960 (Box 168)
- Philippine Islands
- Joint Committee on Educational Television, "Two Years of Progress in Educational Television,", September 1954
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 169)
- Calendar File, May 5, 1942 to August 5, 1942 (Box 170)
- Russell, Bertrand, and WYE's "The False Dilemma of Bertrand Russell"
- Woodrow Wilson Study Group
- Miscellany
- Miscellany (Box 171-173)
- 1988 Increment, 1925-1974 (Box 174-195)
  Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, and reports relating to William Y. Elliott's government service and career at Harvard University, U.S. domestic and foreign policy, and inter-war and post-war Europe.
  - Unsorted material (Box 174)
  - Sound recordings (Box 174)
    Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
    - Dictation of letters to Professor Nelson and Henry Kissinger, July 4 (Box 174)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002622
      Year of recording is unknown. Side 1 is a letter to Professor Nelson, Waterloo University, for Roger Swauson. He gives his opinions on students/scholars. Side 2 is a letter to Henry Kissinger regarding foreign affairs. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a letter to Rosemary Woods, 1968 October 8 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002623
      This is a letter to Nixon's secretary, Rosemary Woods. Elliott offers his insights into important elements of the presidential campaign. Included are the possibility of the House deciding the election, the impact of Wallace, Southeast Asia, and past campaigns. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a letter to President Nixon, April 22 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002626
      Year of recording is unknown. On side 1, Elliot dictates a letter to President Nixon regarding the Black Power movement. He is critical of actions on academic campuses, describing them as armed invasions. He says they want to live on the backs of other, calling it a reversal of slavery. On side 2, Elliot talks about communism and detente. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a recommendation letter for Professor Cromwell to the Executive Secretary of NATO and letter to Winifred Lewis, 1968 November 18 (Box 174)
      General note
      Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002632
    - Dictation of letters to Samuel Huntington and Mr. H. Edward English, 1968 December 3 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002633
      The letter to Samuel Huntington concerns a summer job; that to Mr. H. Edward English, Carleton University, regards a conference on December 13-16. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters, 1968 December 4 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002634
      Letters to Captain Havan B. Page regarding the conference at Little Boston; Dr. Julian K. Knipp, Dean at Tufts, regarding faculty for political science; Mr. and Mrs. James Dickey regarding poetry and round table; Gloria Barion regarding apt. with Moley and Lindly; and the Gulf Oil Corporation regarding returned radio. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters to Marguerite Bouvard and Cecil Crobb, December 4 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002635
      Year of recording is unknown. The letter to Mrs. Marguerite Bouvard concerns a recommendation for her work; the letter to Cecil Crobb, Louisiana State University, concerns Col. Gleb. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a letter to Clayton D. Ford, 1968 December 9 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002636
      The letter concerns his schedule with the Nixon administration and not being able to meet with Mr. Ford. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Sound recording of William Elliott explaining the moral basis for American foreign policy, 1968 November (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002637
      Elliott discusses the intersection of morals and politics. Included in this are discussions of force, Marx, communism, domestic policies (slavery, busing, etc.), and detente with the Soviet Union. Recorded on two Soundwriter discs
    - Dictation of a letter to Francis Wilcox, 1968 December 16 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002639
      Dictation of a letter to Francis Wilcox, Dean of SAIS at John Hopkins, regarding Canadian studies and a conference at Carlton. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters, May 5 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002640
      Year of recording is unknown. Letter to Ward Elliot regarding family and professional issues, letter to Barry Farrell regarding US-Canadian Center at SAIS. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a letter to Mrs. Norman Robertson, June 23 (Box 174)
      Year of recording is unknown. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002641
    - Dictation of letters to Professor Khadum and Richard Fenno, May 2 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002642
    - Dictation of letters to Marguerite Hildebrand, Mrs. Robertson, Randall Ridley, Jesse Wills, Charles Ragland, and Mrs. Alex Stevenson, June 25 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002643
      Year of recording is unknown. The letter to Hildebrand concerns her job; the one to Mrs. Robertson is an addendum to a previous letter clarifying a comment about Rome; the letter to Ridley concerns Ridley's work, Elliot's retirement and finances, and son Ward's wedding; the letter to Wills concerns the SDS and campus community opinions, ROTC, a donation to the archives, and videotapes; the letter to Ragland concerns a wedding, a death, and a visit to Elliott's farm; the letter to Stevenson concerns Mr. Stevenson's death. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters to David Packard, Don K. Price, James T. Murray, June 23 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002644
      Year of recording is unknown. The letter to Packard concerns the farm and California; that to Price is one of "joy and cheer;" the letter to Murray concerns essays. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of a letter to Miss Schurr of the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association, October 14 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002645
      Year of recording is unknown. Letter concerning documents of his wife's qualifications to receive insurance annuity upon Elliott's death. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters to Miss Yudae and Miss Newcomb, 1968 October 14 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002646
      Letter to Yudae concerns income tax and the TIAA annuity. For part 2 of Newcomb letter, see Dictation of letters to Lincoln Gordon and Miss Newcomb. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Dictation of letters to Lincoln Gordon and Miss Newcomb, 1968 October 14 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002647
      The letter to Gordon concerns possible presidential administrations following the 1968 election; that to Newcomb is a continuation of his thoughts on totalitarianism (for part 1, see Dictation of letters to Miss Yudae and Miss Newcomb. Recorded on a Soundwriter disc
    - Elliott dictating his memoirs, disc 23, undated (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002648
    - Dictation of letter and memo concerning the Business Council, October 23-24 (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002649
      Year of recording is unknown. The letter contains W.Y. Elliott's suggestions to the Business Council on the future handling of the takeover of the forces of anarchy and rebellion in the United States, the control of the media of mass communications, the influencing of opinion, and the intimidation of the electorate. Recorded on four Soudwriter discs
    - Sound recording of Elliott describing his objectives in regard to the Principia Public Affairs Conference, 1966 April (Box 174)
      Use copy reference number: 77091_a_0002651
      Elliott discusses the fight against communism, describing the differences between he Soviet Union and communist China. While he believes their objectives are the same, he says they differ in various areas. In the process, topics he covers are Vietnam, Cuba, nuclear weapons, economics, trade with mutual partners, currencies, commodities, culture/the arts, and the Peace Corps. Recorded on five Soundwriter discs
  - Rest of increment not yet described (Box 175-195)
- 1997 Increment (Box 196-197)
  Includes one folder (in box 196) of undated writings related to American foreign policy.
  - Declassified U.S. government records, 1950
    Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
    - 2015 July release of records, 1950 (Box 197)
      Declassified copy of a 15 November 1950 report from Nitze to Marshall with a subject of "Legislative Prospect."